Guide to the Brooklyn Historical Society institutional records ARC.288
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 15: Publications, 1863-2013
  - Sub-series 15.4: The Journal of Long Island History, 1961-1985
    - The Journal of Long Island History and Genealogy Volume I, Number 1, 1961, 1985 (Box 463, Folder 4)
      Includes a partial facsimile of the first edition of The Journal of Long Island History. This edition was published by The Friends of the Long Island Historical Society in an effort to revive the journal.
  - Sub-series 15.5: Publications Committee, 1938-1978
    Sub-series 15.5: Publications Committee includes correspondence related to the development of Society publications, specifically the Long Island Historical Society Quarterly and the Journal of Long Island History. Letters concerning the Quarterly primarily involve essay authors and readers offering comments and questions. For the Journal, the correspondence includes communications with prospective authors and contributors, letters confirming receipt of manuscripts, and notifications of acceptances and rejections of submissions.
    - Publications Committee Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 463, Folder 5)
    - Publications Committee Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 463, Folder 6)
    - Publications Committee Correspondence, 1978 (Box 463, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series 15.6: Publication sales, 1939-1977
    Sub-series 15.6 contains correspondence and promotional materials related to the sale of publications by the Long Island Historical Society. The bulk of the correspondence consists of orders for publications, mainly the Catalogue of American Genealogies in the Library of the Long Island Historical Society and issues of The Journal of Long Island History.
    - Publication sales, 1939, 1953-1954 (Box 463, Folder 8-9)
    - Books, publications, miscellaneous sales and inquiries, 1966, 1968-1970 (Box 464, Folder 1, 3)
    - [Book prices for dealers], 1967 (Box 464, Folder 2)
    - Requests for Catalogue of American Genealogies, 1969-1971 (Box 464, Folder 4)
    - [Publications for sale], 1973-1977 (Box 464, Folder 5, 7,14)
    - Sales -- including copy work, books, reproductions, journals, 1974-1976 (Box 464, Folder 6, 8-12)
    - Publication sales, 1974-1977 (Box 464, Folder 13)
  - Sub-series 15.7: Brooklyn!: An Illustrated History, 1987-1996
    Sub-series 15.7: Brooklyn!: An Illustrated History contains photographs, notes, correspondence, press coverage, and promotional material related to the development and publication of Ellen Snyder-Grenier's book Brooklyn!: An Illustrated History. This book draws on themes highlighted in Brooklyn's History Museum, the Brooklyn Historical Society's first permanent exhibition, to tell the story of Brooklyn. These themes include the Brooklyn Bridge, Coney Island, the Brooklyn Navy Yard, the Brooklyn Dodgers, and Brooklynites.
    Additional material related to Brooklyn's History Museum can be found in Sub-series 8.4: Brooklyn's History Museum, 1984-1996.
    - Book Photo, circa 1996 (Box 465, Folder 1)
    - Book Proposal, circa 1988-1992 (Box 465, Folder 2)
    - [Correspondence], 1996-1997 (Box 465, Folder 3)
    - Ellen Snyder Grenier Photographs, 1997; V1997.67 (Box 465, Folder 4-8)
    - Ellen's Book Notes, circa 1987-1996 (Box 465, Folder 9)
    - Ellen's Paperwork, 1994-1995 (Box 465, Folder 10)
    - Images, Brooklyn Bridge, circa 1987-1996 (Box 465, Folder 11)
    - Images, Brooklynites, circa 1987-1996 (Box 466, Folder 1-3)
    - Images, Coney Island, circa 1987-1996 (Box 466, Folder 4)
    - Images, Dodgers, circa 1987-1996 (Box 466, Folder 5)
    - Images, Miscellaneous, circa 1987-1996 (Box 466, Folder 6)
    - Images, Navy Yard, circa 1987-1996 (Box 466, Folder 7)
    - Images, Neighborhoods, circa 1988 (Box 466, Folder 8)
    - Images, Past BHS Exhibitions, circa 1987-1996 (Box 467, Folder 1)
    - Installation Shots, circa 1991-1994 (Box 467, Folder 2)
    - [Mailer], 1996 (Box 467, Folder 3)
    - New York Society Library Award, 1997 (Box 467, Folder 4)
    - Oral Histories, 1984-1995 (Box 467, Folder 5)
    - Press Coverage, 1997 (Box 467, Folder 6)
    - Quotes for Book, circa 1988-1996 (Box 467, Folder 7-8)
    - Temple University Press, 1993-1995 (Box 467, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 15.8: The Long Island Historical Society newsletter, 1963-1985
    Sub-series 15.8 contains issues of the newsletter published by the Long Island Historical Society. These newsletters document events, personnel changes, exhibitions, committee activities, and other news related to the Society. The publication was originally titled The Milestone and later changed to Notes & News.
    - The Milestone, 1963-1964 (Box 468, Folder 1-2)
    - Newsletter, 1965-1975 (Box 468, Folder 3-13)
    - Notes & News, 1977-1983 (Box 468, Folder 14-20, Box 502, Folder 17)
    - News, 1984-1985 (Box 468, Folder 21-22)
  - Sub-series 15.9: The Brooklyn Historical Society newsletter, 1974-2016; 1986-1999
    Materials in this sub-series are arranged in the order in which they were found. Published copies of the newsletters appear at the end, organized chronologically by publication date.
    The Brooklyn Historical Society's newsletter is a continuation of the Long Island Historical Society's newsletter, established in 1963. Following the Society's name change in 1985, the newsletter underwent a redesign and began offering more details about the society's activities. Subsequent versions of the newsletter were titled "Brooklyn History Comes to Life Magazine" and "Brooklyn History Now."
    Sub-series 15.9 contains correspondence, notes, photographs, mock-ups, drafts, and published copies of the Brooklyn Historical Society's newsletter. The newsletter informed BHS members and visitors about the Society's exhibitions, grant-funded projects, personnel changes, education department initiatives, public programs, acquisitions, fundraising efforts, and other important news items. The bulk of these files originated from BHS's Public Relations Office, which was responsible for compiling and distributing the newsletter, calendar of events, invitations, and press mailings.
    - "Hard Hat" benefit, 1987 (Box 469, Folder 1)
    - The World Theatre, 1986 (Box 469, Folder 2)
    - Membership data, circa 1987 (Box 469, Folder 3)
    - Navy Yard release, 1987 (Box 469, Folder 4)
    - Newsletter, 1986-1988 (Box 469, Folder 5-16, Box 470, Folder 1-7)
    - Press kit, 1988 (Box 470, Folder 8-10)
    - Releases, 1985-1988 (Box 470, Folder 11-14)
    - Shellens lecture series, 1987 (Box 470, Folder 15)
    - Storytelling, 1988 (Box 470, Folder 16)
    - Events calendar, 1988 (Box 470, Folder 17)
    - Wax Musee release, 1987 (Box 471, Folder 1)
    - Mystery Photo responses, 1987-1988 (Box 471, Folder 2)
    - [Notes, drafts, and correspondence], 1986-1988 (Box 471, Folder 3-6)
    - Howard Golden photos, 1990 (Box 471, Folder 7)
    - Green-Wood Cemetery, 1988 (Box 471, Folder 8)
    - LIHS / BHS press coverage, 1974-1992 (Box 471, Folder 9-10)
    - Trivia questions, 1992-1996 (Box 471, Folder 11)
    - [Receipts], 1986-1988 (Box 471, Folder 12)
    - BHS photos, Fall 1992 (Box 471, Folder 13)
    - Staff photos, 1986-1998 (Box 472, Folder 1-4)
    - Special events [photos], 1999-2000 (Box 472, Folder 5)
    - Dinners and fundraisers [photos], 1990-1996 (Box 472, Folder 6-11)
    - BHS board photos, circa 1997 (Box 472, Folder 12)
    - Summer newsletter, 1999-2000 (Box 472, Folder 13)
    - Newsletter correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 472, Folder 14-15)
    - Newsletter mockups, 1986-1988 (Box 505, Folder 8-10)
    - Newsletter, 1986-2003 (Box 502)
    - Brooklyn History Comes to Life, 2012-2016 (Box 473, Folder 1-9)
      Vols. 1-9
  - Sub-series 15.10: Neighborhood history guides, 2005-2010
    Materials in this sub-series are physically arranged alphabetically by file title. Published guides are grouped at the end, organized chronologically by publication date. For the purposes of this finding aid, sub-files relating to particular guides are nested under their respective guides in chronological order.
    In the late 1990s, the education department began developing neighborhood history guides to introduce people to the history of various areas in Brooklyn. Researched and written by historians, each guide offers architectural, cultural, and historical insights into a specific Brooklyn neighborhood. Neighborhoods featured in these guides include Williamsburg, Greenpoint, Red Hook/Gowanus, Bay Ridge/Fort Hamilton, DUMBO/Vinegar Hill/Fulton Ferry, Park Slope, Flatbush, and Fort Greene/Clinton Hill.
    Sub-series 15.10 contains correspondence, meeting notes, drafts, contracts, research files, and published copies of each neighborhood history guide.
    - Application for copyright permission, 2005 (Box 473, Folder 10)
    - Arcadia Publishing, 2004-2005 (Box 473, Folder 11)
    - [Essay drafts], 2005 (Box 473, Folder 13)
      Includes drafts of essays about Sheepshead Bay, Canarsie, Gerritsen Beach, Mill Basin, Bergen Beach, and the Gateway National Recreation Area.
    - Ginko Press [booklist], 2004 (Box 474, Folder 9)
    - Neighborhood history guide [digital] files, circa 2001 (Box 474, Folder 10)
    - Project budget, circa 2004 (Box 474, Folder 11)
    - Project estimate, 2004 (Box 474, Folder 12)
    - [Project proposal], circa 1999 (Box 474, Folder 13)
    - [Research], 1996, 2001 (Box 474, Folder 14-19, Box 475, Folder 1-3)
      These files contain research about the neighborhoods Bedford-Stuyvesant, Coney Island, Midwood, Navy Yard, Park Slope, Sheepshead Bay, and Sunset Park. They all date to 2001 except for portions of the Sunset Park file, which date to 1996.
    - Williamsburg / Greenpoint neighborhood history guide updates, 2004-2005 (Box 475, Folder 10-12)
    - Red Hook / Gowanus Neighborhood History Guide, 2000 (Box 476, Folder 1)
    - Williamsburg Neighborhood History Guide, 2000, 2005 (Box 476, Folder 2)
      - Contract, 2004 (Box 475, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 475, Folder 5-7)
      - [Invoices], 2004-2005 (Box 475, Folder 9)
      - Draft, 2005 (Box 475, Folder 8)
    - Fulton Ferry Landing, DUMBO, Vinegar Hill Neighborhood History Guide, 2001 (Box 476, Folder 3)
      - [Research -- DUMBO], 2001 (Box 474, Folder 16)
    - Greenpoint Neighborhood History Guide, 2001, 2005 (Box 476, Folder 4)
    - Bay Ridge / Fort Hamilton Neighborhood History Guide, 2003 (Box 476, Folder 5)
      - [Draft], 2002 (Box 473, Folder 12)
    - Flatbush Neighborhood History Guide, 2008 (Box 476, Folder 6)
      - [Research], circa 2001 (Box 474, Folder 17)
      - Consultant agreement, 2006 (Box 473, Folder 16)
      - [Walking tours], 2006-2007 (Box 474, Folder 8)
      - [Digital] files, circa 2006-2008 (Box 473, Folder 18)
        Contains 13 optical discs.
      - Potential images, 2006-2008 (Box 474, Folder 5)
      - Outline, 2007 (Box 474, Folder 2)
      - [Meeting notes], 2007 (Box 474, Folder 4)
      - Sample of "Voices", 2007 (Box 474, Folder 7)
      - Brooklyn Collection, 2007-2008 (Box 473, Folder 15)
      - Contemporary Flatbush [research], 2007-2008 (Box 473, Folder 17)
      - [Image list], 2007-2008 (Box 474, Folder 3)
      - Book research [meeting notes], 2008 (Box 473, Folder 14)
      - Draft, 2008 (Box 473, Folder 19-20, Box 474, Folder 1)
      - Proof copy, 2008 (Box 474, Folder 6)
    - Park Slope Neighborhood and Architectural History Guide, 2008 (Box 476, Folder 7)
    - Fort Greene / Clinton Hill Neighborhood and Architectural History Guide, 2010 (Box 476, Folder 8)
  - Sub-series 15.11: General publications, 1913-2013; 1952-1975
    Sub-series 15.11 includes books, booklets, pamphlets, and brochures published by the Society. These publications cover a wide range of subjects, including the Society's collections, its history and activities, and various topics in Brooklyn's history.
    - Long Island Historical Bulletin, 1913 (Box 476, Folder 9)
    - [Jamaica Town Records correspondence], 1914 (Box 476, Folder 10)
    - Jamaica Town Records sales, 1914-1927 (Box 476, Folder 11)
    - LIHS circulars, 1922-1959 (Box 477, Folder 1, 3, 6)
    - The Long Island Historical Society, 1863-1938 (Box 477, Folder 2)
    - Historical Markers and Monuments in Brooklyn, 1952 (Box 477, Folder 4)
    - Outline of the History of Fire Fighting on Long Island, 1955 (Box 477, Folder 5)
    - A Historical Sketch of Ancient Agriculture, Stock Breeding and Manufactures in Hempstead, 1963 (Box 477, Folder 7)
    - Brooklyn and Long Island Sanitary Fair, 1864, circa 1964 (Box 477, Folder 8)
    - A History of Long Island Maps, 1967 (Box 477, Folder 9)
    - The Century Book, contracts and sales, 1962-1966 (Box 477, Folder 10)
    - The Century Book, gifts and acknowledgements, 1968 (Box 477, Folder 11)
    - A Philosophy of History for a Historical Society [address], 1971 (Box 477, Folder 12)
    - The Brooklyn Experience: The Long Island Historical Society's Salute to the Bicentennial, 1975 (Box 477, Folder 13)
    - [Long Island Printing, 1791-1830 by Marguerite V. Doggett], 1978 (Box 477, Folder 16)
    - [Long Island Historical Society brochure], circa 1983 (Box 477, Folder 15)
    - Brooklyn Historical Society, 150 Years Book, 2013 (Box 477, Folder 14)
- Series 16: Financial records, 1862-2020
  The Finance series is arranged into 12 sub-series as follows:
  Sub-series 16.1: Financial statements and audits
  Sub-series 16.2: Budgets
  Sub-series 16.3: Investments
  Sub-series 16.4: Finance administration
  Sub-series 16.5: Legal matters and contracts
  Sub-series 16.6: Government reporting
  Sub-series 16.7: Insurance
  Sub-series 16.8: Loans and financing
  Sub-series 16.9: Building and property finance
  Sub-series 16.10: Ledgers and account books
  Sub-series 16.11: Personnel records
  Sub-series 16.12: Tax documents
  This series contains the financial records of the Brooklyn Historical Society. These include official financial reports and audits, budgets, investments, legal matters and contracts, government reporting, loans and financing, building and property finance, personnel records, and tax documents.
  - Sub-series 16.1: Financial statements and audits, 1935-2010 (Box 570, Box 571, Box 572, Box 573, Box 574, Box 575)
    Official reports and statements on BHS's financial standing.
  - Sub-series 16.2: Budgets, 1997-2019 (Box 576, Box 577, Box 578, Box 579, Box 580, Box 581)
    Budgets, projections, income statements, cash flow reports, and actuals.
  - Sub-series 16.3: Investments, 1881-2010 (Box 582, Box 583, Box 608)
    Documents BHS's investments, including bonds, reports and portfolios.
  - Sub-series 16.4: Finance administration, 1862-1910, 1985-2019 (Box 583, Box 584, Box 608, Box 611)
    Certificates of incorporation [copies], treasurers' records, by-laws, storage records, correspondence, policies and procedures, and the files and notes of Finance personnel.
  - Sub-series 16.5: Legal matters and contracts, 1999-2018 (Box 584)
    Contracts, settlements, claims, incident reports, license agreements, and legal agreements.
  - Sub-series 16.6: Government reporting, 1938-1956, 2003-2020 (Box 585)
    Reports, censuses and surveys created for various state and federal entities.
  - Sub-series 16.7: Insurance, 1886-1889, 1940s, 1997-2013 (Box 585, Box 586, Box 604)
    Documentation of insurance policies held by LIHS and BHS, including for war damage, workers compensation, fine arts, and directors and officers. It also inclues correspondence, documentation of incidents that resulted in insurance claims, and an insurance appraisal by Christie's.
  - Sub-series 16.8: Loans and financing, 2001-2017 (Box 587, Box 588)
    Financing proposals as well as documentation of loans from Commerce Bank, TD Bank, JP Morgan Chase, and Bank of America.
  - Sub-series 16.9: Building and property finance, 1934-2018 (Box 588, Box 589, Box 591)
    Documents relating to properties owned or occupied by BHS, including 128 Pierrepont Street, temporary offices at MetroTech, 55 Water Street and 93 Division Avenue. The sub-series also includes mortgages for a number of properties in the Society's portfolio from the 1930s-1950s, and documents relating to a 2003 Department of Design and Construction (DDC) project.
  - Sub-series 16.10: Ledgers and account books, 1863-1974 (Box 592, Box 593, Box 594, Box 595, Box 596, Box 597, Box 598, Box 599, Box 600, Box 601, Box 602, Box 603, Box 604)
    Various ledgers, cash books, account books and other bound financial records.
  - Sub-series 16.11: Personnel records, circa 1980s-2020 (Box 607, Box 608, Box 609, Box 610)
    Personnel files, including offer letters, evaluations, resignation letters, separation agreements, and so forth. Additional files include staff lists, memos, policies, job descriptions, and summer intern records from the 1990s.
  - Sub-series 16.12: Tax documents, 1958-2020 (Box 605, Box 606, Box 608)
    Documents related to taxes, including property and real estate taxes, tax returns (including form 990), IRS determination letters, payroll taxes, form 5500, and sales tax.
- Series 17: Audiovisual materials
  This series consists of audiovisual material in various media documenting LIHS and BHS exhibitions, educational programs, meetings, and more. Portions of this series have been digitized.